<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Deaths advantage; opened in a sermon preached at Northampton, at the funeral of Peter Whalley Esq; then mayor of the said town. And now upon the earnest desires of his friends published by Edward Reynolds. D.D.</title>
            <author>Reynolds, Edward, 1599-1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E501_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E912_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865240</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865240</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168456</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168456)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 79:E501[2], 137:E912[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Deaths advantage; opened in a sermon preached at Northampton, at the funeral of Peter Whalley Esq; then mayor of the said town. And now upon the earnest desires of his friends published by Edward Reynolds. D.D.</title>
                  <author>Reynolds, Edward, 1599-1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho Newcomb for George Thomason, and are to be sold at his shop at the Rose and Crown in Pauls Church yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy (E.912[6]): "May 30" also Thomason has added "Stationer" following Peter Whalley's name and "St" before 'Pauls'.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168456:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Deaths Advantage; Opened in a SERMON PREACHED The laſt Summer at <hi>Northampton,</hi> AT THE FUNERAL OF Peter Whalley <abbr>Eſq</abbr> Then Mayor of the ſaid Town.</p>
            <p>And now upon the earneſt deſires of his Friends publiſhed by <hi>Edward Reynolds,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho Newcomb</hi> for <hi>George Thomaſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Roſe and Crown</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church yard, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:168456:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:168456:2"/>
            <head>To the Honorable John Crew Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving been prevailed with by the earneſt deſires of thoſe who were nearly related unto that worthy Gentleman, at whoſe Funeral this Sermon was preached, to let it, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had been it ſelf ſo long buried) ſomething unſeaſonably revive and go abroad into the world; I have taken the boldneſs to prefix ſo honorable a name as yours before it, upon a double account; one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating unto the deceaſed <hi>Gentleman,</hi> the other unto <hi>my ſelf.</hi> For the former, if we may take the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a wiſe and worthy man by the affection which he beareth, and choyce which he maketh of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>Examples,</hi> whoſe prudence and piety to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w, I may truly, and therefore without flattery to you or him pronounce this dear Friend now with God, a very <hi>wiſe,</hi> and a very <hi>good</hi> man, having been frequently an ear-witneſs of the ſingular Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor he did bear to your perſon (in mentioning of
<pb facs="tcp:168456:3"/>whoſe zeal and care to promote the glory of God, the truth of the Goſpel, the intereſt of Religion, and good of your Country, he did greatly delight to expatiate) and whom he did propoſe to himſelf as a ſpecial pattern for his imitation. For mine own part, as I have the ſame reaſons which moved him, to bear an honorable and high eſteem towards your perſon, and the gifts and graces of God beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon you; ſo you have by your abundant favours to me, and particularly your earneſt and ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous endeavors to have preſerved my Station in the Univerſity, when changes in the State cauſed changes there, laid ſo great a debt upon me, as I have no way to diſcharge, but onely by putting you over to the beſt Pay-maſter, and in my prayers commending you unto him, who doth not forget your labour of love. To his gracious Protection I commend you, and all the branches and intereſts of your Family, and remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble and moſt obliged Servant, ED. REYNOLDS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168456:3"/>
            <head>THE Gain of Death.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. 1.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For to me to live is Chriſt, and to dye is Gain.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle having <hi>ſaluted</hi> theſe <hi>Philippians,</hi> and teſtified his ſincere <hi>love</hi> unto them, and hearty <hi>prayers</hi> for them in the firſt eleven Verſes; doth in the next place endeavor to <hi>comfort</hi> them againſt any offence or trouble which they might ſuſtain by occaſion of his <hi>ſufferings</hi> for the Goſpel, <hi>verſ.</hi> 12, 13. aſſuring them that they tended to the defence thereof; many being thereby <hi>provoked,</hi> and by the example of his <hi>courage</hi> and comfort <hi>animated to ſpeak the Word without fear, verſ.</hi> 14. And although ſome indeed had evil and <hi>envious intentions</hi> to reproach his Apoſtleſhip, and to add affliction to his bonds,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168456:4"/>yet Chriſt being preached, he did <hi>rejoyce</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his own <hi>ſufferings,</hi> as knowing that by the benefit of their <hi>prayers,</hi> and by the <hi>ſupplies</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Chriſt, his own <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and the <hi>glory</hi> of the Lord ſhould thereby be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15-20. And if the Lord may be thus <hi>magnifiea,</hi> and himſelf <hi>ſaved,</hi> if his <hi>life</hi> may tend to the <hi>honour</hi> of Chriſt, and his <hi>death</hi> to his own <hi>advantage,</hi> he is moſt indifferent and contented to yeeld to Gods holy will either way; for, ſaith he, <hi>to me to live is Christ, and to die is gain.</hi> If I <hi>live,</hi> my work, my converſation, my miniſtry will be wholly to ſerve and <hi>glorifie</hi> him; and if I <hi>dye,</hi> my death will not onely be <hi>glorious</hi> unto him, but <hi>gainful</hi> unto me, I ſhall be <hi>ever with the Lord, which is beſt of all.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore is at a ſtand, in a <hi>ſtrait</hi> betwixt two, which to chuſe: On the one ſide Chriſt will be <hi>magnified</hi> in the <hi>edification</hi> of his Church; on the other ſide he will be <hi>magnified</hi> by the <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> of his ſervant; the one will be <hi>fruitful</hi> to the <hi>Philippians;</hi> and the other <hi>gainful</hi> to himſelf. He is wholly therefore indifferent whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he <hi>live or dye,</hi> becauſe Chriſt will be both ways an <hi>advantage</hi> unto him, and he ſhall be both ways <hi>ſerviceable</hi> to the glory of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>We ſee the coherence, connexion and ſcope of theſe words. Some verſions, as ours, make them two diſtinct Propoſitions, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt, To me to dye is gain.</hi> Some others make them but one propoſition, thus, <hi>In life and in death,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I live or dye, <hi>Chriſt is to me gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168456:4"/>
            <p>In the words there are two parts conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Firſt, The <hi>Propoſitions</hi> themſelves. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The <hi>ſpecification of the Subject</hi> to whom they belong.</p>
            <p>The Propoſitions are, according to both read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, theſe three. Firſt, <hi>To live is Chrſt.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>To Dye is Gain.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Chriſt is both in life and in death gain.</hi> The ſpecification of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> of theſe Propoſitions, to whom they belong, <hi>To Me,</hi> a Beleever, who am willing and deſirous that Chriſt may be <hi>magnified in my body,</hi> whether it by my <hi>life</hi> or by my <hi>death,</hi> as being much more tender and ſollicitous of his honour, then of mine own particular ſafety.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, <hi>To live is Chriſt,</hi> or Chriſt is life unto us. It is true, many men <hi>live,</hi> who are without <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the world, an animal or a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral life to themſelves, to other men, to carnal, to ſecular, to ſinful purpoſes; but being <hi>alienated</hi> from the <hi>life of God,</hi> we may ſay of them as the Apoſtle doth of ſenſual and delicate Widows, that they are <hi>dead whilſt they live.</hi> Our true <hi>life</hi> is founded in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>life</hi> of Chriſt; <hi>Becauſe I live you ſhall live alſo,</hi> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h. 4.19. <hi>He that hath the Son hath life, he that hath not the Son hath not life.</hi> 1 Joh 5.12.</p>
            <p>Now Chriſt is our <hi>life</hi> in every way of <hi>cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi> Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid Fr: Gomar: To.</hi> 1. p. 288.</note> He is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Author and <hi>efficient</hi> of our life, whether we ſpeak of life <hi>natural;</hi> In him was <hi>life,</hi> and the <hi>life was the light of men; he lighteth every man that cometh into the World,</hi> Joh. 14.2. <hi>By him all things conſiſt,</hi> Col. 1.17.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168456:5"/>
               <hi>In him we live</hi> and move, and have our being, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. <hi>He formed us in the belly,</hi> his hands made us and faſhioned us round about, <hi>Job</hi> 10.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139 15, 16. In every work of <hi>continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Creation</hi> the Son worketh as well as the Father. <hi>My Father worketh hitherto,</hi> ſaith he <hi>and I work, Ioh.</hi> 5.17. Or whether we ſpeak of life <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> the life of Grace; <hi>I live,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me,</hi> Gal. 2.20. In him is the primitive ſeat of life and grace, from whom it is diffuſed upon his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy For as the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Members</hi> are anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>one ſoul,</hi> ſo Chriſt &amp; his Church by <hi>one ſpirit.</hi> we being joyned unto the Lord <hi>are one Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Aug. de Gen. ad lit. l.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 5 <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note> Or laſtly, whether we ſpeak of <hi>Life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> the life of Glory, this our <hi>life is hid with Chriſt in God, and when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, we ſhall alſo appear with him in glory,</hi> Col. 3.3, 4: Of theſe two eſpecially <hi>the Life of Grace</hi> and <hi>the Life of Glory,</hi> Chriſt is the efficient cauſe, <hi>per modum pretii,</hi> as a Meritorious Procurer of it, laying down no leſs a price then his own life to purchaſe ours; <hi>For we are bought with a price,</hi> 1 Cor 6.20. and by vertue of that price we are <hi>quickened together with him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gomar. to.</hi> 3. <hi>diſp</hi> 15 <hi>&amp; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker de deſcenſ. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 49.</note> Epheſ. 2.5. 2. <hi>Per modum Principii</hi> by his Holy Spirit faſhioning us to his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>likeneſs;</hi> for being a Second <hi>Adam,</hi> he is unto us a <hi>quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. and having <hi>life in himſelf</hi> doth derive it upon whom he will, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.21 26. <hi>As the living Father hath ſent me, and I live by the Father, ſo he that eateth me ſhall live by me,</hi> Joh. 6.57.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt is the <hi>matter</hi> of our <hi>Life:</hi> As
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168456:5"/>
               <hi>meat</hi> is the matter on which life feedeth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Tract.</hi> 26 <hi>in Joan. Euſeb. cont. Marcel. cap.</hi> 12.</note> and by which it is preſerved; ſo Chriſt is the <hi>ſpiritual Manna, the bread which came down from Heaven,</hi> of which they who eat ſhall live, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.51. The <hi>Sacrifices</hi> after they were <hi>offered</hi> for expiations, were many times <hi>eaten</hi> for the comfort and reviving of thoſe that offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d them. Chriſt therefore, who was our <hi>Paſsover,</hi> having <hi>offered</hi> himſelf as a <hi>propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation,</hi> to take away our ſin by the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> of himſelf, was thereupon pleaſed to inſtitute his <hi>Laſt Supper,</hi> and therein to ſet forth himſelf as that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>food</hi> whereby the life of Grace in his people is nouriſhed and preſerved.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt is the very <hi>form</hi> of ſpiritual life in a <hi>Beleever,</hi> in which reſpect he is ſaid <hi>to live in us,</hi> and to be <hi>formed</hi> and faſhioned in us, as the childe is ſhaped in the womb of the Mother, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.19. and this both as <hi>forma eſſentialis,</hi> the very ſoul that actuateth a beleever, he is <hi>a quickening Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. If Chriſt be in you, the body is dead becauſe of ſin, but the Spirit is life becauſe of righteouſneſs, Rom.</hi> 8.10. and as <hi>forma exemplaris,</hi> the Idea, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and pattern of our life, for he hath given <hi>us an example</hi> that we ſhould follow his ſteps, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui eſſe vult ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi &amp; non tibi nihil eſſe incipit inter omnia.</hi> Bern. in contr. Serm. 20.</note> Chriſt is the <hi>end</hi> and ſcope at which our whole life is to aim and to be directed; it muſt be wholly <hi>conſecrated</hi> unto him; nothing in all our concernments muſt be ſo dear unto us as <hi>Chriſt;</hi> whether we live we muſt <hi>live to him,</hi> or whether we dye we muſt <hi>dye to him;</hi> becauſe for this end he both died and roſe again, that he might be <hi>the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168456:6"/>Lord both of the dead and of the livings,</hi> Rom. 14.7, 8, 9. therefore as by bringing forth <hi>much fruit we do glorifie the Father,</hi> Job. 15.8. ſo alſo do we thereby honour the Son, out of whoſe fulneſs we receive grace for grace; for he that <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth not the Son, honoureth not the Father,</hi> Joh. 5.23. This ſeems here principally intended, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt:</hi> My life, time, ſtudies, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments are wholly taken up in the things of <hi>Christ,</hi> that he may have honour and ſervice by me. Wicked men live <hi>to themſelves,</hi> to them to <hi>live</hi> is <hi>luſt</hi> and vanity; they follow their own wils, they walk in the imagination of their own hearts; they rule themſelves by no counſel but their own carnal and corrupt wiſdom, as it is ſaid of <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boham,</hi> that he ſet up a worſhip <hi>which he had deviſed of his own heart,</hi> 1 Reg. 12.33. and the the people profeſſed to <hi>Jeremy</hi> that they would do whatſoever ſhould go forth out of their <hi>own mouth, Jer.</hi> 44.17. They direct all they do <hi>to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> looking after onely their own gain, eaſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, credit, advantage; faſting, eating, drinking <hi>to themſelves,</hi> and aſſembling themſelves for <hi>corn and wine, Zach.</hi> 7.6. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.14. They withdraw themſelves from that ſubjection, and ſubordination wherein God hath placed them, and do in effect ſay as <hi>Pharaoh, Who is the Lord that I ſhould obey his voice! Ex.</hi> 5.2. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is is a very ſtrange folly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our <hi>ſalvation</hi> and the <hi>glory of Chriſt</hi> are twiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, as the coherence of the 19. and 20. verſes of this Chapter doth demonſtrate. When we neglect his <hi>glory,</hi> we forfeit our own <hi>ſalvation;</hi> and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168456:6"/>when we ſeek our own <hi>ſalvation,</hi> he eſteemeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>glorified</hi> thereby. As when a great ſtone doth fall from an Arch, the little ones that were bound and knit in by it do fall for company; ſo when men do neglect the <hi>great end</hi> of living to the honor of Chriſt, they do greatly endanger all their own ſubordinate ends thereby.</p>
            <p>What is it then for <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be our <hi>life,</hi> or for a man truly to ſay, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt?</hi> It is Firſt, In our <hi>hearts</hi> to acknowledge him for <hi>our Lord,</hi> unto whom we owe our time, and ſtrength, our fear, and honour, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.11. <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in our <hi>lives,</hi> to do every ſervice with <hi>good will,</hi> and <hi>in ſingleneſs of heart as unto him,</hi> Eph. 6.5, 6, 7. to do it by a warrant from his word, <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſay,</hi> Pſ. 85.8 <hi>Proving what is the good, and perfect, and acceptable will of God,</hi> Rom. 12.2. and what it is which Chriſt would have us to do, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6. To ſet him <hi>always before us,</hi> and to do every thing as in <hi>his preſence,</hi> and with a deſire to approve our hearts in well doing unto him, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.8. for as he behaved himſelf towards his Father, doing always thoſe things that <hi>pleaſed him, Joh.</hi> 8.25. 6.38. ſo are we to behave our ſelves towards him, who as he hath made us the <hi>Sons</hi> of his Father by <hi>Adoption, Joh.</hi> 20.17. ſo is he himſelf our <hi>Father</hi> by <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and calleth us in one reſpect his <hi>Brethren,</hi> and in another his <hi>Children, Heb.</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. To do every thing unto his <hi>glory,</hi> as <hi>veſſels fitted for our Maſters uſe,</hi> and <hi>prepared unto every good work,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.21. To value our <hi>life</hi> not cheifly for it ſelf,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168456:7"/>but for the <hi>ſervice</hi> which therein we are to do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Lord: <hi>I count not my life,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>dear unto my ſelf, ſo that I may finiſh my courſe with joy, and the Ministry which I have received of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> Act. 20.24. And herein likewiſe we imitate his example, who in conformity to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> of his Father did himſelf lay down his own life for his ſheep, and became <hi>obedient unto death, even the death of the croſs,</hi> a ſervile, an ignomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Lipſ. de Cruce. cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Caſaub. in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. exercit.</hi> 16 <hi>c.</hi> 77.</note> a curſed death, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.11, 15, 18. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.8. This it is for a man to ſay, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt;</hi> my thoughts, ſtudies, aims, purpoſes, imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, do all fix and terminate upon him, how I may bring <hi>glory</hi> to his name, how I may promote his <hi>intereſts</hi> and Kingdom; how I may <hi>live the reſt of my time in the fleſh, not unto mine own luſts, but unto his will,</hi> unto whom my ſoul and ſalvation was dearer then his own life. Since his <hi>blood</hi> was my <hi>price,</hi> his <hi>glory</hi> muſt be my <hi>buſineſs.</hi> For he therefore <hi>died for All, that they which live, ſhould not henceforth live unto themſelves, but unto him which died for them and roſe again,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1, 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 20. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15.</p>
            <p>We ſee how <hi>Chriſt is life;</hi> Let us next enquire to whom he is ſo. <hi>To me,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>to live is Chriſt.</hi> There is much of the life of Religion in <hi>Pronowns</hi> and <hi>Adverbs,</hi> in <hi>perſons</hi> and the <hi>manner</hi> of doing things. To thoſe whom the Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, he is life; to thoſe that <hi>beleeve he is precious,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7. To others he is a <hi>ſtone of ſtumbling,</hi> and a <hi>rock of offence,</hi> and his Goſpel <hi>a ſavor of death unto death.</hi> He is not at all in their thoughts or
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168456:7"/>cares to pleaſe or glorifie him. They are not at a point, ſo he may have honour, whether it be by their life or death. But ſo they may have pleaſure or profit, ſo their carnal deſires may be gratified, and their intereſts ſecured, let what will become of his name or honor. Therefore let us make ſure the <hi>Pronown</hi> here, <hi>To me,</hi> that I am one who am willing Chriſt ſhould be <hi>magnified</hi> by me any way, whether <hi>by life</hi> or <hi>by death;</hi> otherwiſe we cannot ſay, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far all runs very ſmoothly unto Chriſtian ears. <hi>To live is Chriſt,</hi> he <hi>our Lord;</hi> therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his <hi>ſervice</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> muſt our whole life be conſecrated and devoted. No difficulty in all this.</p>
            <p>The next Propoſition ſeemeth more ſtrange and paradoxal, that to <hi>Dye</hi> ſhould be <hi>Gain.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arrian. Epictet. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. <hi>Senec. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onſol. ad Mart. &amp; Polyb. &amp; Ep.</hi> 24 30, 66. M. <hi>Antonin. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>Plutarch. conſol. ad Apollon.</hi>
               </note> Many Philoſophers have ſpoken many kinde and flarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words concerning <hi>Death;</hi> That it is the <hi>end, ſolution, period, remedy</hi> of all our cares, ſorrows, labors, fears; a <hi>Debt,</hi> a <hi>Tribute,</hi> a <hi>Sleep,</hi> an <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,</hi> or <hi>Haven,</hi> a <hi>reſt,</hi> a <hi>quiet Repoſe</hi> after all our griefs and miſeries: But none I think did ever go ſo far as to make it <hi>Gain;</hi> and it may ſeem to be no other nor better gain, then that which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks of, <hi>Act.</hi> 27.21. <hi>A gaining of loſs;</hi> for what kind of <hi>gain,</hi> would one think can there be found in that, the very formal being and nature whereof doth conſiſt in nothing but <hi>loſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is in it the <hi>loſs</hi> of all a mans <hi>Subſtance, His houſe knows him no more,</hi> Job 7.10. His Lands, his Place, his Tenants, Rents, Revenues
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168456:8"/>own him no longer. If there were a <hi>judgement at Law</hi> given againſt a man, overthrowing his whole eſtate, ſtripping him of his <hi>houſe</hi> over his <hi>head,</hi> the <hi>mony</hi> in his purſe, the <hi>corn</hi> in his Barns, the <hi>Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel</hi> in his fields, the <hi>cloaths</hi> on his back, leaving him as naked as the world at firſt found him, would any man call this <hi>gain: Death</hi> is juſt ſuch a <hi>judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> leaveth a man no more <hi>land</hi> then his <hi>grave,</hi> no more <hi>cloathes</hi> then his <hi>Shrowd,</hi> no more <hi>houſe</hi> then his <hi>Coffin.</hi> No difference but this; in the one <hi>Judgment</hi> poſſibly a ſtranger, in the other a Son, or a Kinſman ſucceeds; but as to a mans ſelf it is all one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But when all theſe things are gone, haply <hi>friends</hi> may recruit a man again, as they did <hi>Job,</hi> Chap. 42.11.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Polyb. hiſt. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Fruitur diis i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratis.</hi> Juv.</note> We read of the incredible bounty of Princes and States to the people of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> after they had been ſorely ruined by an earthquake, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that their calamity proved an advantage unto them. But in death there is a <hi>loſs of friends,</hi> as well as of Eſtate, Wife, Children, all part at the <hi>grave,</hi> and never meet till the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though means and friends be all loſt, yet if a man could keep poſſeſſion of <hi>himſelf,</hi> it may be his head or his hand, his wit or his labour would repair his loſſes again: But <hi>Death</hi> is the loſing of a <hi>mans ſelf,</hi> no <hi>hand</hi> left to work, no <hi>head</hi> left to contrive; it tears a man aſſunder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n himſelf, and ſends his parts as far diſtant as either Heaven or Hell are from the Grave. Now after all theſe <hi>loſſes,</hi> of Eſtate, of Friends, of Wiſdom, of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168456:8"/>ſtrength, of a mans very ſelf, what poſſible room is there left for Gain, when he that ſhould enjoy it is himſelf loſt?</p>
            <p>All this notwithſtanding, <hi>God</hi> muſt be <hi>true,</hi> and <hi>every man a lyar. Death is Gain,</hi> and <hi>Gain</hi> we muſt finde in it before we leave it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let us take it at the worſt view which a Beleever can have of it, as it is an <hi>Enemy</hi> for ſo the Apoſtle calls it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. And ſo it was eſteemed by Chriſt himſelf, who though in <hi>love</hi> to us, and in <hi>obedience</hi> to his father, he ſubmitted unto it, yet teſtified his <hi>natural deſire</hi> to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined it, when with ſtrong crys he prayed once and again, <hi>O my Father, if it be poſsible let this cup paſs from me.</hi> You may not without ſhew of reaſon ſay, What <hi>Gain</hi> is to be expected from an <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my?</hi> Many times <hi>Friends</hi> themſelves, when it comes to the point of <hi>gain,</hi> to this queſtion, <hi>Who will ſhew us any good,</hi> are ſhie, and draw in their friendſhip. <hi>Laban</hi> though <hi>Jacobs</hi> Father in law, grudged him the benefit of that bargain which himſelf had before moſt willingly conſented unto; <hi>Joab</hi> was <hi>Abſoloms</hi> friend, yet <hi>Abſolom</hi> burnt up his corn.</p>
            <p>Yet we may not deny,
<note place="margin">Vid. Plutarch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>h. de capienda ab hoſtibus uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utate.</note> but that a man may have <hi>gain</hi> by an <hi>enemy,</hi> as poiſon unto ſome creatures affordeth nouriſhment: <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>elephus</hi> had his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtume opened by the dart of an enemy, which was intended for his hurt. Thoſe <hi>Roſes</hi> they ſay are ſweeteſt which grow near unto <hi>Garlick;</hi> the neatneſs of an <hi>Enemy</hi> make a good man the better. And therefore the wiſe Roman, when <hi>Carthage</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168456:9"/>the Emulous City of <hi>Rome</hi> was deſtroyed, ſaid truly, Now our affairs are in more danger and haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard then ever before. When <hi>Saul, Davids</hi> Enemy, Eyed and perſecuted him, this made him walk more circumſpectly, pray more, truſt in God more; He kept his mouth <hi>with a bridle while the wicked were before him,</hi> Pſal. 39.1. An hard <hi>knot</hi> in the wood drives a man to the uſe of his <hi>wedges.</hi> A ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious <hi>Enemy</hi> that watcheth for our halting, will make us look the better to our <hi>ways.</hi> And ſo <hi>death</hi> by the nearneſs thereof, and by the frequent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation thereupon, makes us more careful of our great <hi>accompt,</hi> more ſollicitous to make ſure our <hi>peace</hi> with God, to <hi>wean</hi> our hearts from worldly and periſhing comforts, to lay up <hi>a good foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> for the time to come, that we may obtain eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, to get <hi>a City which hath foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, all this <hi>Gain</hi> is from <hi>Death</hi> at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> while we are out of its poſſeſſion. Is there any <hi>Gain</hi> from ſuch an enemy while we are under his <hi>power?</hi> Yes, even here there may be <hi>gain;</hi> was not the <hi>fire</hi> an enemy to the <hi>three Children?</hi> were not the <hi>Lions</hi> enemies to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel?</hi> yet they were rebuked; <hi>When a mans ways pleaſe the Lord, he maketh his enemies at peace with him,</hi> Prov. 16.7. <hi>Laban</hi> purſued <hi>Jacob</hi> in great anger, <hi>Eſau</hi> meets him, as we may ſuppoſe, with hoſtile purpoſes; but the Lord by his power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful providence over-ruled their hearts, that they could not hurt him. <hi>Saul, Davids</hi> Father-in-law,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168456:9"/>perſecutes him; and <hi>Achiſh</hi> the King of <hi>Gath,</hi> from whence <hi>Goliah</hi> came, whom <hi>David</hi> had not long before ſlain, and who could not but for that reaſon be hated at that place, gives him entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: God can make <hi>Moab a covert for his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſts,</hi> as he was unto the Father and Mother of <hi>David, Iſa.</hi> 16.4. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.3, 4. Though <hi>Death</hi> be an enemy, the Lord can weaken it, diſarm it, pull out the ſting of it, and make us at peace with it.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, All this is rather <hi>harm</hi> ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, then <hi>gain</hi> obtained. Is there any more proper and gennine <hi>gain</hi> to be found in an Enemy, ſuch an Enemy, having us under his power and poſſeſſion? ſurely yes. We finde the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> bitter Enemies to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> furniſhing them with <hi>Jewels of ſilver, Jewels of gold and Raiments, Exod.</hi> 3.21, 22. Was not the <hi>Whale</hi> that ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jonah</hi> an <hi>enemy,</hi> a very <hi>type</hi> of our <hi>enemy</hi> here, as our Saviour tells us? <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.39, 40. Yet by it was <hi>Jonah</hi> carried ſafe to land, he regained life by that which devoured him; he had been <hi>drowned</hi> in the <hi>Sea,</hi> if the <hi>fiſh</hi> had not found out the <hi>Shore</hi> for him. Were not the waters of the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and of <hi>Jordan</hi> enemies to thoſe that ſhould go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the midſt of them? yet through theſe did <hi>Iſrael gain</hi> liberty out of bondage, victory over <hi>Pharoah</hi> and his hoſt, and poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed <hi>Rest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take it in the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Here men are <hi>abſent from the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. as <hi>Jonah</hi> is ſaid to have <hi>fled from his preſence,</hi> caſt out into a Sea of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168456:10"/>cares, troubles, fears and ſorrows; <hi>Death</hi> as the <hi>Whale</hi> devours us, and lands us at a better <hi>ſhore,</hi> leads us from the thraldom of <hi>Satan,</hi> from the <hi>temptation</hi> and ſufferings, and <hi>fiery Serpents</hi> which we meet with in the <hi>wilderneſs</hi> of this <hi>world,</hi> and brings us into our <hi>Heavenly Reſt.</hi> So then even under the notion of an <hi>enemy</hi> here is <hi>gain</hi> from <hi>death.</hi> As a <hi>Lamprey</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed delicate meat when the <hi>ſting</hi> of the back is taken out; as the waters of <hi>Marah</hi> were made ſweet by the <hi>tree</hi> which was caſt into it; ſo <hi>death,</hi> being by the croſs of <hi>Chriſt</hi> purged of its venome and bitterneſs, is become uſeful and gainful unto us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us view <hi>Death</hi> on the better ſide; for it is as a <hi>plaited picture,</hi> on the one ſide it looks like a grim and angry <hi>enemy,</hi> as deſtructive to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; on the other ſide, it hath a more calm and <hi>friendly aſpect,</hi> as reconciled unto us by Chriſt. It is as a <hi>Servant</hi> ſent from a Father to call his Son home; as a <hi>Nurſe</hi> which taketh the <hi>Childe</hi> in her arms to carry it to the Mother; it is a <hi>depoſitary</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the cuſtody of the body, and ſhal give an exact accompt thereof unto Chriſt. He by his holy <hi>body</hi> hath <hi>ſanctified</hi> the <hi>grave,</hi> &amp; made it a <hi>bed</hi> to ſleep in. We find <hi>Angels at either end of Chriſts grave,</hi> Joh. 20.12. They keep the Saints not onely in their <hi>ways,</hi> but in their <hi>graves.</hi> The <hi>Jaylor</hi> who before did beat <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſcourge him, and thruſt him into the inner priſon; being converted, treated him after another manner, <hi>waſhed his ſtripes, brought him into his houſe, and ſet meat
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168456:10"/>before him,</hi> Act 16.33, 34. Such a change there is in <hi>death;</hi> before, the <hi>ſpirit of bondage</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it with a chain and ſcourge, it kept the ſoul down under the fear and dread of it. But now, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a beleever by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is ſo far altered, that it is become part of his <hi>dowry</hi> and portion, numbred up by the Apoſtle amongſt thoſe good things which with Chriſt are graciouſly beſtowed upon us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.</p>
            <p>We will conſider the <hi>Gain</hi> we have by this Friend, firſt <hi>privatively,</hi> then <hi>poſitively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Privately,</hi> It freeth us from all other evil, and toilſom labours, which we were, by the curſe pronounced againſt <hi>Adam,</hi> ſubject unto. It is a kinde of <hi>Canaan,</hi> a <hi>Reſt,</hi> a <hi>Sabbath</hi> unto beleevers; <hi>write</hi> ſaith the Lord from heaven to his Apoſtle, <hi>Bleſſed are they that dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their labors,</hi> Rev. 14.13. they <hi>enter into peace, they reſt in their beds,</hi> Iſa 57.2.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They reſt from the toilſom captivity and <hi>tyranny</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> a <hi>burden</hi> under which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, as too heavy for them to bear; <hi>There is no reſt in my bones becauſe of my ſins; mine iniquities are grown over mine head; as an heavy burden, they are too heavy for me,</hi> Pſal. 38.3.4, 6, 7, 8. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle calleth it a <hi>weight,</hi> and an encompaſſing ſin; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri Agoniſtic. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Methedius a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Epiphan. haereſ.</hi> 64.</note> a fat and heavy body wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſeth for an Athletick imployment. This body of luſt being deſtroyed, they are <hi>made perfect. Heb</hi> 12.23. As <hi>Ivy</hi> which hath gotten its roots into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the joynts of a wall, can never he qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e killed, till the wall it ſelf be demoliſhed; ſo ſin and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168456:11"/>being deeply ſeated in the whole nature of man, is never quite ſlain and ſubdued till the whole frame be taken down and diſſolved.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Tholoſ. Syntagma juris, l.</hi> 31. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>Beſtias Aſiaticae preſſurae. Tertul. de reſurrect. carnis, cap.</hi> 48.</note> They reſt from the <hi>buffets</hi> and temptations of <hi>Satan;</hi> it was a ſore conflict for the Apoſtle to fight with <hi>Beaſts at Epheſus,</hi> whether they were truly or Metaphorically ſuch, beaſtly men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. but this combate was nothing to the <hi>meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger of Satan,</hi> to the roarings of that Lion; how rampant and outragious he will be againſt the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God, when the Lord is pleaſed to leng then his chain, and to give him liberty; what diſmal <hi>fears,</hi> what helliſh <hi>impreſsions,</hi> what <hi>fiery darts,</hi> what black and horrid <hi>ſuggeſtions</hi> he will amaze the ſouls of poor ſinners withal, the examples and experiences of many of Gods afflicted people can abundantly teſtifie, inſomuch that <hi>their ſoul chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſtrangling,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Job</hi> 7.15. Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by death tranſlated into <hi>Abrahams boſom,</hi> they are far removed out of Satans reach; he was thrown <hi>down from heaven,</hi> and can never ſhoot up any darts, or come near any of Gods ſervants there to affright or annoy them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They reſt from the cares, ſorrows, ſnares, toils, temptations of <hi>the world;</hi> the <hi>examples</hi> of ſinners do not <hi>endanger</hi> them, the ſight of their <hi>filthy converſation</hi> doth no longer <hi>afflict</hi> them, the fear of their <hi>cruelties</hi> and perſecutions doth no more trouble them; there <hi>the wicked ceaſe from troubling, and there the weary be at reſt; there the priſoners reſt together, they hear not the voice of the oppreſſor,</hi> Job 3.17, 18.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:168456:11"/>
            <p n="4">4. They reſt from the <hi>difficulties</hi> of <hi>duty</hi> it ſelf; thoſe hard conflicts which the heart hath againſt corruption to keep it ſelf cloſe unto God; for though the <hi>ſpirit be willing, yet the fleſh is weak,</hi> Matth. 26.41. and though <hi>to will be preſent with us,</hi> yet <hi>how to perform the thing that is good we finde not,</hi> Rom. 7.18, 19, 21.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, As they are delivered from theſe <hi>paſt evils,</hi> as brands ſnatched out of the burning, ſo are they likewiſe taken away from <hi>evils to come,</hi> as <hi>Lot</hi> was from the deſtruction of <hi>Sodom,</hi> when the Angel by a merciful violence laid hold on him and brooght him forth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.16. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Poſitively,</hi> this gain by death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the many real good things which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive with it and by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It brings us <hi>home</hi> to our Country and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; here in this life Gods ſervants are <hi>Pilgrims, Strangers, Sojourners,</hi> amongſt enemies, ſuch as neither know nor value them; we are called out of the world, and ſeparated from it, <hi>not numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Nations,</hi> living by different and contrary Laws; and hence it is that the <hi>world hates us,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.9. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1. Hence the <hi>Body</hi> is called a <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Digeſt. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum ſignificat. l.</hi> 239. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2. M. <hi>Anton. l.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 17. <hi>Tertul. de reſur c.</hi> 41. <hi>Diodor Sic.</hi> 1. <hi>M. Anton. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ſect.</hi> 11.</note> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13, 14. in alluſion to the <hi>Tabernacles</hi> wherein the Patriarchs ſojourned as <hi>ſtrangers, Heb.</hi> 11.9. unto which <hi>pilgrimage,</hi> and unfixed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the Apoſtle there oppoſeth a <hi>City which hath foundations,</hi> verſ. 10. a ſure houſe, an abiding <hi>Kingdom which cannot be ſhaken, Heb.</hi> 12.28.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168456:12"/>Here indeed we are ſaid to be <hi>in Chriſt,</hi> and Chriſt in us, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. but there we ſhall be <hi>with Christ,</hi> and in his preſence, which the Apoſtle tells us is beſt of all, <hi>much better</hi> then our beſt condition here, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. Here we are in the <hi>ſame family</hi> indeed (for the Church in heaven, and the Church on earth is but <hi>one family,</hi> Epheſ. 3.15.) but we are yet but in the <hi>lower rooms</hi> of the family, in the <hi>work houſe;</hi> death leads us to the <hi>upper chamber,</hi> to the <hi>Banquetting-houſe,</hi> to better company, where we ſhall ſee, and know, and love, and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs Chriſt perfectly, and herein is the anſwer of Chriſts prayer, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. <hi>Father, I will, that they alſo whom thou haſt given me, be with me, where I am, that they may behold my glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It eſtates us in <hi>life;</hi> takes away one life to carry us to another and a better. That life which we leave, is mortal and periſhing; that which we go unto is durable and <hi>abounding, Joh.</hi> 10.10. The <hi>ordinary Manna</hi> which <hi>Iſrael</hi> gathered for their daily uſe, did preſently corrupt and <hi>breed worms, Exod</hi> 16.20. But that which was laid up before the Lord, the <hi>hidden manna</hi> in the Tabernacle, did keep without putrefaction, verſ. 33. So <hi>our life,</hi> which we have here in the <hi>wilderneſs</hi> of this world, doth preſently vaniſh and corrupt, but our life which is kept in the Tabernacle, our <hi>life which is hid with Chriſt in God, Col.</hi> 3.4. that never runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death. <hi>Natural life</hi> is like the river <hi>Jordan,</hi> empties it ſelf into the <hi>Dead Sea;</hi> but <hi>ſpiritual
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168456:12"/>life</hi> is like the <hi>waters</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhallow at the firſt grow deeper and deeper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a River which cannot be paſſed thorow; water continually <hi>ſpringing</hi> and running forward <hi>into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life, Ezek.</hi> 47.4, 5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. 7.38. — <hi>Haec brevis eſt, illa perennis aqua.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It makes us perfect in our ſpiritual part;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Stuck. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq conviv. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>The ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, Heb.</hi> 12.23. it gives us our white and triumphal <hi>robes, Rev.</hi> 6.11. 7.14. It fits us to be <hi>preſented unto God without ſpot or wrinkle, Epheſ.</hi> 5.27. the bodies of the Saints when they were dead <hi>were waſhed, Act.</hi> 9.37. both as a pledge of the <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and alſo as an <hi>Emblem</hi> and teſtimony of that clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and <hi>purity,</hi> wherein death did deliver their ſouls up unto God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It keeps our relicks and remainders ſafe for a glorious <hi>reſurrection,</hi> will give a faithful and a juſt <hi>accompt</hi> of all that it hath received, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore in <hi>honour,</hi> what is received in <hi>diſhonour,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42, 43. It will ſay to us as the keeper of the Priſon to <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 16.36. <hi>The Lord hath ſent to let you go, now therefore depart, and go in peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee the Paradox cleared, the difficulty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved; the gain demonſtrated; onely we muſt remember it is not gain to all, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. To <hi>Beleevers</hi> as ſuch, and therefore onely to them. To wicked and impenitent ſinners that die in their ſins, death is a <hi>King of terrors, Job</hi> 18 14. A Jaylor, a tormentor, with his keys, his ſhakels, his hot iron, his halter, his ax, his gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168456:13"/>He is ſtill a ſtinging and a fiery ſerpent, a <hi>trap-door</hi> unto hell. Death is never our <hi>gain,</hi> but where Chriſt is our <hi>life;</hi> he to whom to <hi>live</hi> is is <hi>luſt,</hi> and not Chriſt; to <hi>dye</hi> is <hi>loſs</hi> and not <hi>gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now ſince <hi>Gain</hi> is one of the <hi>Diana's</hi> of the world,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Auguſt. in Pſal.</hi> 48.</note> every one will ſay, <hi>who will ſhew us any good?</hi> Pſal. 4.6. Our wiſdom muſt be to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh <hi>true gain</hi> from counterfeit, to make <hi>godlineſs our gain,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 6.6. for then death will be our Gain too. There is ſome Gain like Manna in the houſe, <hi>periſhing Gain,</hi> expoſed to <hi>moth and ruſt. Matth.</hi> 6.19. Gain proper to one place or Country, like ſome <hi>farthing-tokens,</hi> which are current in one Town or Shop, and ſignifie nothing in another: Such is worldly wealth, current here, but is not returnable or tranſportable into another world,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. De Nino Phaenix Colophon apud Athenaeum. l.</hi> 12</note> 
               <hi>when a man dieth he carrieth nothing away, his glory ſhall not deſcend after him,</hi> Pſ. 49.17. But there are <hi>durable riches,</hi> Prov. 8.18. A treaſure of good <hi>works</hi> which will <hi>follow</hi> a man into another world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. this is the <hi>gain</hi> we ſhould look after, to <hi>lay up a foundation in ſtore againſt the time to come, that we may lay hold on eternal life,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.19.</p>
            <p>Now ſith <hi>Death is gain,</hi> let us conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in what manner this <hi>Gain</hi> may be <hi>deſired.</hi> In anſwer whereunto we ſay, 1. That death is conſiderable two ways: One way as it affecteth <hi>nature,</hi> the other as it relateth to a <hi>ſupernatural end.</hi> In the former reſpect as an <hi>evil, Nature</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors it, and ſhrinks from it, and had much rather
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168456:13"/>be clothed upon, that mortality might be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of life. But as an unavoidable <hi>medium</hi> to a better condition, ſo it may be deſired; as ſick and bitter <hi>phiſick</hi> is deſirable, not <hi>per ſe,</hi> but in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto <hi>health;</hi> and dangerous chargeable voyages by Sea, are not in themſelves beneficial at all, but onely as they are neceſſary to make rich returns from remote Countries. <hi>Mercatura est amittere ut lucreris.</hi> It is good husbandry to ſell all for an invaluable pearl.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Death</hi> is not to be <hi>deſired</hi> out of <hi>fretfulneſs, paſsion, wearineſs</hi> of life, <hi>impatience</hi> of ſufferings, as <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Jonah</hi> deſired it, <hi>Job</hi> 3.20-23. <hi>Jon.</hi> 4.3. and in great anguiſh men are apt to do, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8 3. but in <hi>faith,</hi> and an humble ſubmiſſion to the will of God, out of a <hi>wearineſs</hi> of the body of <hi>ſin,</hi> and <hi>pilgrimage</hi> in the valley of tears, ſuſpiring after the <hi>preſence</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>conſummation</hi> of holineſs, thus it may be deſired. So <hi>Jacob wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the ſalvation of God, Gen.</hi> 49.18. So <hi>Simeon</hi> deſired to <hi>depart in peace, Luk.</hi> 2.29, 30. and ſo our Apoſtle here, <hi>I deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better,</hi> Phil. 1.23.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We may not for all this uſe any compendious way to be partakers of this <hi>gain,</hi> we may not neglect our <hi>body,</hi> nor ſhipwrack our <hi>health,</hi> nor do any thing to <hi>haſten death</hi> becauſe we ſhall <hi>gain</hi> by it. <hi>He that maketh haſte</hi> even this way <hi>to be rich, ſhall not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> Prov. 28.20. When men grew weary of the long and tedious compaſs in their Voyages to the <hi>Eaſt Indies,</hi> &amp; would needs try a more compendious way by the <hi>North-weſt</hi> paſſage, it ever proved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168456:14"/>
               <hi>our times are in Gods hands,</hi> as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.15. and therefore to his holy providence we muſt leave them. We have <hi>work</hi> to do, and therefore muſt not be ſo greedy of our <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> our <hi>reſt,</hi> as not to be willing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with our <hi>working day,</hi> our <hi>labour.</hi> A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed frame of heart, like the Apoſtles here, an <hi>holy indifferency</hi> of ſoul, either to ſtay and <hi>work,</hi> or to go and <hi>reſt,</hi> is the beſt temper of all.</p>
            <p>I conclude all with but naming the laſt Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition from the other reading, <hi>Chriſt in life, in death is gain</hi> unto beleevers. If the Apoſtle <hi>live,</hi> he ſhall <hi>ſerve</hi> Chriſt; if he <hi>dye</hi> he ſhall <hi>enjoy</hi> him; if he <hi>live,</hi> he ſhall <hi>glorifie</hi> him by his <hi>miniſtry,</hi> if he <hi>dye,</hi> he ſhall <hi>glorifie</hi> him by his <hi>martyrdom.</hi> When Chriſt is ours, every condition, life or death, proſperity or adverſity is <hi>gainful</hi> to us. It is hard to ſay whether it be better for a wicked man to <hi>live</hi> or <hi>dye,</hi> being in both equally miſerable; If he live, he encreaſeth his <hi>ſin;</hi> if he <hi>die,</hi> he entreth upon his <hi>ſorrow.</hi> But unto a godly man either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition is comfortable and bleſſed; his <hi>life</hi> is fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, his <hi>death</hi> is peaceable; the <hi>grace</hi> of Chriſt is manifeſted in <hi>his life,</hi> and the <hi>glory</hi> of Chriſt is manified in his <hi>death.</hi> Let us be careful to ſecure the <hi>Pronown</hi> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To Me,</hi> that we be ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> was, who <hi>rejoyce in that Chriſt is preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> though we ſhould ſuffer by the means, who are <hi>not aſhamed of the afflictions of the Goſpel,</hi> but are willing that Chriſt may be <hi>magnified in our body, whether by life or by death,</hi> and then we may bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude as our Apoſtle doth, whether <hi>I live</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168456:14"/>or whether <hi>I die,</hi> Chriſt will in both conditions be <hi>advantage</hi> unto me.</p>
            <p>COncerning this worthy Gentleman, who with <hi>one ſpring</hi> of his ſoul gave ſo ſudden a leap from Earth to Heaven; I confeſs I have been ſo ſurpriſed with ſorrow, that I thought it hardly poſſible for me to undertake this ſervice, but that I muſt have covered over my affections, and his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, as the <hi>Painter</hi> did <hi>Agamemnons</hi> grief for <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> with a vail of ſilence.</p>
            <p>He was a copious ſubject, a man one of a thouſand as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaks; which <hi>way ever</hi> we take the view of him, we ſhall <hi>finde him</hi> to be as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotles</hi> character is of his honeſt man, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a four-ſquare man, that had in <hi>every capacity a Baſis</hi> of honeſty and integrity to fix upon.</p>
            <p>How tender and dear an <hi>Husband,</hi> how loving and careful a <hi>Father,</hi> how wiſe and prudent a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer</hi> of his domeſtical affairs, your eyes and their ſorrows can abundantly teſtifie.</p>
            <p>Towards <hi>others</hi> abroad, I do not know a man <hi>fuller of love</hi> and faithfulneſs, more <hi>ready,</hi> more <hi>active to lay out himſelf</hi> upon the good and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of his friend. There are <hi>ſome drags</hi> very wholſom, but very bitter; good in the operation but unkind in the palate; and ſome <hi>friends</hi> are ſuch, <hi>real</hi> in their love, but <hi>moroſe</hi> in their expreſſions of it, that a man is almoſt afraid of their very kindneſſes. But this our dear friend was <hi>full of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168456:15"/>ſweetneſs as of fidelity.</hi> His love was not like a <hi>Pill,</hi> that muſt be wrapped in ſomething elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man can ſwallow it, but the <hi>candor</hi> and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reneſs</hi> of his diſpoſition made his <hi>love</hi> as <hi>amiable</hi> as it was <hi>uſeful</hi> unto his friends; ſo that he well deſerved the character given to one of the Roman Emperors, <hi>Neminem unquam dimiſit triſtem.</hi> He was indeed in his diſpoſition <hi>made up of love</hi> and ſweetneſs, <hi>of a balſom nature,</hi> all for healing and helpfulneſs.</p>
            <p>He was not a <hi>friend</hi> in <hi>pretence</hi> and comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that can <hi>bow</hi> handſomly, and <hi>promiſe</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatically, and <hi>ſpeak</hi> plauſibly, and forget all; but he was <hi>ſerious</hi> and cordial in his affection. Some <hi>mens love</hi> is like ſome <hi>plants</hi> in the water, which have <hi>broad leaves</hi> on the ſurface of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but ſcarce any root at all; lik <hi>Lemons</hi> cold within and hot without; <hi>full expreſsions, empty intentions, ſpeak loud,</hi> and <hi>do little.</hi> Like <hi>Drums</hi> and <hi>Trumpets,</hi> and <hi>Enſigns</hi> in a battel, which make a noiſe and a ſhew, but act nothing: But this our dear Brother was an <hi>active friend,</hi> his reality exceeded his expreſſions: His <hi>words</hi> were the <hi>window</hi> of his heart, truly as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls them, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the notifiers of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And his <hi>fidelity</hi> to his friend was ever <hi>ſeconded</hi> with <hi>wiſdom;</hi> as our Saviour ſaith of <hi>John the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> he was a <hi>burning</hi> and a <hi>ſhining</hi> Lamp, we may ſay in this caſe of him, he had not onely an <hi>ardent</hi> but a <hi>prudent</hi> love was not onely <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> to intend good, but <hi>able to counſel</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168456:15"/>it: <hi>Some friends are like a vine, fruitful</hi> but <hi>weak;</hi> their love is ſweet, but their ſtrength ſmall; he as able by his wiſdom to adviſe, as ready by his love to help and tender.</p>
            <p>Nor was this diſpoſition of his narrow and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted</hi> towards a few, but it was <hi>diffuſive.</hi> The mildneſs and moderation of his ſoul made him will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to do good to all, and ſo far as would conſiſt with integrity, to preſerve every man from peril. Some mens love is like ſome <hi>flowers,</hi> which open onely towards the <hi>Sun,</hi> which come out onely in the <hi>hotteſt ſeaſons,</hi> like the <hi>load-ſtone</hi> that points onely one way, and bend onely towards them that do not need it: But <hi>his love</hi> would grow in the <hi>ſhade</hi> as well as in the <hi>Sun;</hi> and though it were ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally directed to thoſe of the houſhold of faith, yet he had learned of the Apoſtle to do good to all men, and to ſpeak evill of none.</p>
            <p>But it is not enough <hi>for a man to do good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> though he could to all if he remain an <hi>enemy to himſelf.</hi> Like <hi>Shel-fiſhes</hi> which breed <hi>pearls</hi> for others to wear, but are <hi>ſick</hi> of them themſelves; lik a <hi>Mercury Statue,</hi> which ſhews the way to others, but ſtands ſtill it ſelf; like a whetſtone which ſharpeneth the knife, but is blunt it ſelf. If thou be wiſe, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> be wiſe for thy ſelf. Many men are like <hi>Plutarchs Lamiae,</hi> which had <hi>eyes</hi> for <hi>abroad,</hi> but were <hi>blinde at home,</hi> like <hi>Bees</hi> that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good honey, but are ſmothered themſelves: But our dear Brother had <hi>an eye inward</hi> was wiſe to the intereſts of his own ſoul. Like the <hi>Cynamon tree,</hi> which lets not out all its ſap into leaves and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168456:16"/>fruit which will fall off, but keeps the principal of its fragrancy for the bark which ſtays on, <hi>like a tree planted by the water ſide,</hi> which though it let out much ſap to the remoter boughs, yet is ſpecially careful of the <hi>root,</hi> that that be not left dry. And in truth, <hi>what profit would it be</hi> to a man, if he could <hi>help and heal</hi> all the <hi>ſick men</hi> of the world, and be incureably ſick himſelf? If he could get <hi>all the men</hi> on the earth, all the <hi>Angels</hi> in heaven to be his friends, and have ſtill <hi>God</hi> for his enemy? If he could ſave others, and then loſe his own ſoul? to be <hi>like the ſhip,</hi> Act. 27. broken to peeces it ſelf, though it helped others to the ſhore? Like <hi>thoſe that built the Ark</hi> for <hi>Noah,</hi> and were drowned themſelves. Herein therfore he ſhewed himſelf <hi>truly a wiſe man,</hi> that he took <hi>care of his own ſoul:</hi> Some men are <hi>like Achitophel,</hi> very careful to ſet their houſes in order, but then caſt away their <hi>ſouls:</hi> But our dear Brother though he had by the variety of his imployments, <hi>the cares of Martha upon him,</hi> was yet ſpecially mindful of <hi>Maries unum neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> the care of his own ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And he did not take up his Religion with the times, that he might <hi>magis uti Deo quam frui,</hi> make gain godlineſs; as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> who would be Jews when the Jews proſpered, and enemies to them when they ſuffered; but he was, as is ſaid of <hi>Mnaſon,</hi> Act. 21.16. <hi>an old Diſciple,</hi> a <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of Religion in the <hi>worſt times,</hi> when piety was nick-named preciſeneſs, and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from evil made himſelf a prey, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.15. <hi>Temporibuſque malis auſus es eſſe bonus,</hi> did dare
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168456:16"/>to be good in bad times. <hi>Religion</hi> ſometimes is like <hi>oyl,</hi> gets higheſt, and the <hi>faeces</hi> and <hi>amurca</hi> are at the bottom, when the horn of the righteous is exalted, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.10. Sometimes it is like <hi>gold in the Mine, lies deep</hi> and <hi>depreſſed,</hi> like the ſap of a tree <hi>in winter,</hi> fain to ſhrink under ground. There <hi>are many Summer Chriſtians,</hi> will be religious in the <hi>ſun ſhine;</hi> our dear Brother was a <hi>winter Chriſtian,</hi> kept his religion in the <hi>ſtorm:</hi> and as then he was, ſo he continued <hi>a ſteady Chriſtian,</hi> a <hi>ſhip well bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced</hi> with ſound <hi>knowledge,</hi> and rooted <hi>ſincerity,</hi> and love of the truth; not carried about with every wind of doctrine. It is ſaid of Chriſt he is <hi>yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day and to day the ſame, Heb.</hi> 13.8. Chriſtians ſhould therein imitate him, and having tried all things, hold laſt the good, and with purpoſe of heart cleave to God.</p>
            <p>God hath beautified ſeveral of his <hi>ſervants</hi> with ſeveral <hi>Graces;</hi> we read of <hi>Jobs</hi> patience, <hi>Moſes</hi> his meekneſs, <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, <hi>Maries</hi> love, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> devotion, <hi>Solomons</hi> wiſdom, <hi>Apollo</hi> his elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; our dear Brother was <hi>eminent in many</hi> likewiſe, in meekneſs and mildneſs of ſoul, he was a man <hi>of an amiable and calm temper,</hi> yet ſweetly quickned with zeal for Gods glory. He was a great <hi>lover of an able Miniſter,</hi> and of the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt ſo diſpenſed; an eminent grace in theſe times, when <hi>poor Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> (it is well they go together, they are good company) ſuffer together from many whom we cannot wonder at for being ſo much enemies to others, who are ſo little friends to their own ſouls; he that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>values
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168456:17"/>his own life, may eaſily deſpiſe another mans. But by the way, it were well if the <hi>deſpiſers of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> would conſider that <hi>little children</hi> who play the wantons with their meat, are likely not long after to know what difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a ſmarting rod, and a wholſom dinner. We may have Ordinances taken away from us too ſoon, let not us take them away from our ſelves.</p>
            <p>We have viewed him in his <hi>private</hi> capacity as a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> if we conſider him in his <hi>publick</hi> as a Magiſtrate, we ſhall finde how great a loſs the Town and Country had of him in this regard, as his friends and the Church of God in the other. <hi>Some men are like Vines,</hi> very good for fruit, but you cannot make a beam or a pin of them to hang any veſſells thereon, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 15.3. to ſuch things Magiſtrates are compared, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.23, 24. But our <hi>Brother</hi> was like the <hi>Wallnut tree,</hi> good both for <hi>fruit</hi> and for <hi>timber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His <hi>fitneſs</hi> for Magiſtracy appeared in this, that being not an aged man, he was <hi>twice called</hi> to the Majoralty of this Town, and once to ſerve for the ſame more publickly. <hi>Tully</hi> derided <hi>Heraclid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Temnites</hi> that he lived to old age, and never attained thoſe honors in his Country which others uſually did arrive at; it could not be ſaid ſo of him, he was <hi>of ſo dexterous a ſpirit</hi> that one may ſay of him as <hi>Livy</hi> did of <hi>Cato, Natum adid unum diceres quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque ageret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the more <hi>conſiderable,</hi> in that he was not <hi>originally brought up</hi> to ſervices of a <hi>publick</hi> nature. It is noted for the honor of <hi>Alphenus Varus</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:168456:17"/>that having been bred <hi>in a ſhop</hi> at a private <hi>trade,</hi> he proved ſo learned and eminent a Lawyer, that he wrote <hi>collectanea juris,</hi> ſome of which are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the pandect, and was afterwards <hi>Conſul</hi> of the City. And we read in humane ſtories of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathocles, Juſtinus, Primiſlaus, Pinctus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who by their wiſdom and abilities were raiſed from Trades and Farms to great Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Our dear Brothers <hi>publick imployments</hi> were <hi>not</hi> the <hi>fruits of his own ambition,</hi> but of the <hi>free love</hi> of other men, who for his wiſdom, fidelity, and fitneſs called him thereunto. And truly, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit man he was for them; an able man, fearing God, loving truth, hating covetouſneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. He had a <hi>publick ſpirit</hi> very ready to en tertain and promote every thing which tended to the general good.</p>
            <p>Some men are like the <hi>Prophets Vine, Hoſ.</hi> 10.1. bring fruit onely to themſelves and are empty to all the world beſides: But <hi>he was one</hi> who <hi>could deny</hi> himſelf, and his private intereſt, to ſerve the publick, as <hi>natural bodies</hi> will forſake their own proper motions to prevent a publick breach upon the univerſe. <hi>Pompey</hi> being diſſwaded from an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition hazardous to himſelf, but uſeful to the publick, returned this anſwer to his friends, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe eſt ut eam, non ut vivam;</hi> It is neceſſary for me to go, it is not neceſſary for me to live. And truly beſides his <hi>Wiſdom, Zeal</hi> for God, <hi>Dexterity</hi> to ſet forward good works, he <hi>had one excellent Character</hi> for Magiſtracy, he was a man of a <hi>milde</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:168456:18"/>and <hi>meek ſpirit.</hi> I call this an excellent temper for Magiſtracy. If it were not ſo, <hi>the Lord</hi> would not have choſen <hi>Moſes,</hi> the meekeſt man on earth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3. nor <hi>David</hi> who was as a weaned childe, to be the Ruler of <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 131.1, 2. <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates will meet with many things to provoke paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> difficulties in buſineſs, multitudes of imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, croſ sand mutinous diſtempers in ill-diſpoſed people, prophanations and diſhonors done to the name of God (which exceedingly ſtirred <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19.) therefore they had need have <hi>milde</hi> and <hi>compoſed</hi> ſpirits; patience is the effect of power, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.</p>
            <p>Thus he lived in his private capacity, a dear Husband, a tender Father, a faithful friend, a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtian: Thus he lived in his publick capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, a wiſe, zealous, ſelf-denying, publick-hearted, meek-ſpirited Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>And now as he ſaid, <hi>oportet imperatorem ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem mori—</hi> And another, <hi>Epiſcopum concionantem,</hi> that it was honourable for a Commander to die in his <hi>Arms,</hi> and a Biſhop in his <hi>Pulpit:</hi> So the Lord ordered the death of our dear Brother with this circumſtance of honor in it, that he <hi>died a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> in his Office; <hi>Aaron</hi> was ſtripped of his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal Ornaments on the mount, where he was called to die, <hi>Num.</hi> 20.25, 26. And this our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did put off his <hi>Robe</hi> to put on his <hi>Shrowd;</hi> his Magiſtracy yeelded to his mortality.</p>
            <p>His death was <hi>ſudden in it ſelf,</hi> ſo was <hi>old Elies,</hi> a good man; but it is <hi>not ſudden to a Beleever,</hi> whoſe holy life fits him or it; for <hi>ſanctity</hi> is a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168456:18"/>preparation unto death then <hi>ſickneſs.</hi> It is all one if a man come to heaven, whether it be by a <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> or by a <hi>Rapture,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> was caught up thither, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Well, he is with Chriſt,</hi> which is beſt of all, though we be without him; <hi>the care of his friends</hi> muſt be by <hi>moderation of ſorrow</hi> to teſtifie their aſſured hope of his happineſs. And the <hi>care of the Town</hi> muſt be to teſtifie <hi>their love</hi> unto him, with chuſing a wiſe, holy, faithful, zealous man to ſucceed him, who may carry on thoſe good works, which he had the happineſs to begin, but not to finiſh by reaſon of a greater happineſs.</p>
            <p>We leave him with our Apoſtles Motto upon him, <hi>To him to Live was Chriſt, and therefore to Dye was Gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
